Srivas Chennu

srivaschennu.github.io
+1 408 581 3109
srivas@gmail.com



Profile

Machine learning R&D team leader at Apple. Have developed ML models across multiple application domains. Led research team of scientists. 14+ years of post-PhD R&D experience spanning the US, UK, Germany and India. Research featured by the BBC, Wired Magazine, and New Scientist. Have consulted for multiple start-ups.

Research

Co-authored nearly 100 peer-reviewed publications in academic journals, cited nearly 4000 times. h-index of 28 (as of Oct 2023). Have published research on a wide range of topics including computational neuroscience, time series analysis, deep learning, reinforcement learning, Bayesian methods, graph network analysis and probabilistic inference.

Employment

Senior Research Manager

Apple

2023-present

Lead a team of scientists building ML-powered personalized experiences for Apple services. Have led projects to create and ship large-scale recommender systems powered by deep learning and reinforcement learning. Have applied LLMs to extract insights from textual data to power highly visible customer-facing features. Have deep knowledge of ML with big data, and on-device ML with privacy.

Research Manager Apple 2019-present

Lead team building models for predicting and optimizing user engagement across Apple's services. Helped improve user acquisition and retention, producing measurable increase in revenue. Co-led adoption of interpretable reinforcement learning. Developed Bayesian inference framework powering App Store's <u>product page optimisation</u> feature for AB testing. Published papers at KDD and DSAA.

Assistant Professor, Team Leader

University of Kent, UK

2016-2019

Led health care AI research team of 4 scientists. Delivered software for measuring biomarkers of consciousness using time series modelling and network analysis, enabling improved bedside evaluation of patients. Secured independent research funding. Published papers in high-impact journals. Research featured in a BBC Panorama special *The Mind Reader: Unlocking My Voice.*

Visiting Researcher

The Alan Turing Institute, UK

2018

Developed ML models for automated diagnostics of brain states using EEG time series.

Senior Research Associate

University of Cambridge, UK

2010-2016

Developed spectral coherence methods and causal models of EEG time series for predicting conscious states during anaesthesia and after severe brain injury. Research profiled in the *BBC*, *New Scientist*, *Scientific American*, *Der Spiegel*, and *Wired*. Gave public at *Wellcome Collection* and *New Scientist Live*.

Graduate Research Assistant

Fraunhofer Institute, Germany

2005

Worked on an EU-funded project on QoS-aware broadband internet using resilient optical access. networks.

Graduate Research Assistant

Hamburg University of Technology, Germany

2005

Developed convex optimisation and linear programming solutions for industrial applications. Published an algorithmic methodology for decentralization of real-time control systems.

Member of Technical Staff

Oracle Corporation, India

2002-2004

Worked as software engineer in the *Oracle Reports* team, a part of Oracle's *Internet Application Server* platform. Build internal QA tools in Java, C++ and shell scripts.

Consulting

DataTiger (Marketing optimisation start-up acquired by Apple)

2018

Applied ensemble machine learning for predicting customer retention in online multiplayer games. Built unsupervised learning models for personalising timing of marketing communications.

Rsrchxchange (FinTech start-up)

2017

Built neural network-based NLP model for content similarity analysis of financial research reports. Developed latent factor models with Apache Spark to build financial research recommender models.

Education

PhD in Computer Science

University of Kent, Canterbury, UK

2006-2009

Thesis title: *The temporal spotlight of attention: computational and electrophysiological explorations* (approved with no corrections)

MSc in Information and Communication Systems Hamburg University of Technology

2004-2006

Hamburg, Germany

Overall ECTS grade: 1.3 (Very Good; Passed with Distinction)

BEng in Computer Science and Engineering

Visveswaraiah Technological University

1998-2002

Bangalore, India

Overall percentage score - 81.46% (First Class with Distinction)

Skills

- Big Data Modelling, Cloud Computing on AWS
- Parametric, Non-parametric and Bayesian Statistics
- Signal Processing and Time Series Analysis
- Graph Theory and Network Analysis
- Tools: tensorflow, pytorch, pyro, scipy, pandas, pyspark
- Languages: Python, MATLAB, JAVA, C++, C

- Deep Neural Networks
- · Probabilistic Machine Learning
- Applied Artificial Intelligence
- Computer Networking and Security

Selected Publications

Chennu, Maher, Pangerl et al. 2023. <u>Rapid and Scalable Bayesian AB Testing</u>. 10th IEEE Conference on Data Science and Advanced Analytics, DSAA 2023.

Chennu, Martin, Liyanagama & Mohr. 2021. <u>Smooth Sequential Optimisation with Delayed Feedback</u>. *Workshop on Bayesian Causal Inference in Real-World Interactive Systems, ACM SIGKDD*.

Patlatzoglou, Wolff, Gosseries, Bonhomme, Laureys & **Chennu**. 2020. <u>Generalized Prediction of Unconsciousness</u> <u>during Propofol Anesthesia using 3D Convolutional Neural Networks</u>. *The 42nd International Conference of the IEEE Engg. and Biology Society*.

Chennu, Annen, Wannez, Thibaut et al. 2017. <u>Brain networks predict metabolism, diagnosis and prognosis at the bedside in disorders of consciousness</u>. *Brain*, 140(8), 2120-2132.

Chennu, Finoia, Kamau, Allanson et al. 2014. <u>Spectral signatures of reorganised brain networks in disorders of consciousness</u>. *PLOS Computational Biology*, 10(10), e1003887